Okay so today's דף daf is מ"ו mem vav and we pick
up on the bottom of מ"ה עמוד ב' mem hey amud bet
back and our discussion is about the משנה mishna speaks about somebody
falling asleep and if you're not conscious can you establish that as
the place of your עירוב? eruv? According to רבי יוחנן בן נורי
Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri you can; according to the חכמים Chachamim you
cannot. Interestingly, according to the חכמים Chachamim if you cannot, so where
is the place of your עירוב? eruv? So the משנה mishna gives
you the same status as if you had gone out of the
תחום. techum. You're not in any particular place; you only have your
ד' אמות. four amos. Some of the ראשונים Rishonim ask why is
that different than like the case we see later in the גמרא
Gemara about the rain that falls on שבת Shabbos or the boat
that lands on שבת Shabbos when it was higher than י' טפחים
ten tfachim that at least it can get אלפיים אמות two thousand
amos from where it lands. But here they're not so lenient; they
say well there it wasn't yet in the zone, here you're in
the zone and you just weren't conscious. Anyway, it's not so clear,
but if you didn't have that place then you're left with ד'
אמות four amos and that's the debate. And the גמרא Gemara says
maybe it's not just a maybe, it's not about a person who's
not conscious, maybe it even goes deeper, maybe it would even be
about inanimate objects. And that then becomes the question whether inanimate objects
that normally follow their owner, but if they are ownerless, do they
are they defined as the place where they began שבת Shabbos אלפיים
אמות two thousand amos or does it go by the person who
finds them? So by analogy or similarly a person who's unconscious, does
he establish his place אלפיים אמות two thousand amos or does he
not have a place for שבת Shabbos and is limited to ד'
אמות? four amos? So now the גמרא Gemara continues with this and
it says the following: כי אתא
לקמיה דרב יוסף, ki ata lekamei deRav Yosef, when אביי Abaye came
to
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, it starts with the word דרב יוסף, deRav
Yosef, it's on מ"ה עמוד ב', mem hey amud bet, it's about
twelve lines from the bottom, maybe fifteen lines from the bottom, starts
the word for רב יוסף. from Rav Yosef. So this was אביי
Abaye who was telling over this whole discussion about whether you go
based on the whole ברייתא braisa about rain and where rain lands
and so on, that if that rain that fell before שבת Shabbos
is defined by where it fell, that's the idea that חפצי הפקר,
chafzei hefker, non-owned objects,
are קונה שביתה, kona shvisa, define their שבת Shabbos to begin where
they are and that's being made as parallel to the position of
רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri. So now it says
like this: כי אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף, ki ata lekamei deRav Yosef,
when אביי Abaye came to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, אמר ליה, amar
lei, הכי קאמר רב ספרא, hachi ka'amar Rav Safra, this is what
רב ספרא Rav Safra said, והכי אהדרי ליה, ve-hachi ahadrei lei, and
this is what I responded to him. I'm sorry, we read that
already, I'm sorry, we pick up later down, about eight lines from
the bottom at the two dots אמר מר. amar mar. The line
starts with the word ליה. lei. Okay, so אמר מר: amar mar:
ביום טוב הרי הן כרגלי כל אדם. be-Yom Tov harei hen ke-ragli
kol adam. So this is the case that if the rain fell
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, so obviously its place wasn't established on
when יום טוב Yom Tov began when it was on the ground,
and so then it does not have any particular place and it's
defined by the person who finds them. הרי הן כרגלי כל אדם.
harei hen ke-ragli kol adam. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי, v'amai,
why is this true? לקני ליה שביתה באוקיינוס, likni lei shvisa be-Okianos,
why doesn't it acquire its שביתה, shvisa, meaning its its, oh my
god, got to get more tape, my little jury-rigged contraption is having
problems.
Okay, anyway ואמאי, v'amai, לקני ליה שביתה באוקיינוס, likni lei shvisa be-Okianos,
why doesn't it acquire where it rests, where it begins שבת Shabbos
in the ocean? You see the word אוקיינוס Okianos and ocean, right?
If you make the K into a C.
No, they mean whatever ocean it began in, I mean they sort
of believed, they believed that there was like one huge ocean that
surrounded that surrounded everything. So anyway, alright, I'm not sure, anyway, so
let it start שבת, Shabbos, fine we'll use that if we need
to, let it start שבת Shabbos in the ocean, meaning where was
it when שבת Shabbos began? When שבת Shabbos began it was in
the ocean, so why don't we say that that's where it gets
its אלפיים אמות two thousand amos from the ocean and then based
on the water cycle and it evaporates and it comes back down
and it's outside of its אלפיים אמות two thousand amos and you
can't use the rain at all? So why don't we say that?
So the גמרא Gemara says
לימא דלא כרבי אליעזר, lema d'lo ke-Rebbi Eliezer, let's say this contradicts
רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, דאי כרבי אליעזר, de-ee ke-Rebbi Eliezer, if it
were like רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, האמר כל עולם כולו ממי אוקיינוס
הוא שותה, ha-amar kol olam kulo mi-mei Okianos hu shoteh, he says
the whole world drinks from the water of אוקיינוס, Okianos, meaning again
I think this was an understanding that basically it was one ocean,
so all of based on the water cycle, all water eventually comes
from that ocean. And the גמרא Gemara assumes that it happens within
twenty-four hours, so anything that's raining on שבת, Shabbos, ערב שבת erev
Shabbos it started in the ocean.
They assumed rain water came from the ocean? Why would they assume
that? I know. Why would they make that,
right, because, yeah, so that's why it's quoting רב יוסף Rav Yosef
who was of that of רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer who's of that
opinion. So it's saying maybe this proves not like רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer that the water comes from elsewhere than the ocean. So let's
take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says, but the basic
point is why don't we say it
assumed it was on the ground before שבת Shabbos began and it
evaporated after. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's funny also the
whole idea that you consider it the same object after the whole
process of evaporation and condensation and so on. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says: אמר amar, רב יצחק הכא בעבים שנתקשרו מערב יום טוב
Yom Tov, עסקינן *Amar Rav Yitzchak hacha b'avim shenitkashru m'erev Yom Tov
askinan*. Ah, it didn't evaporate on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. These clouds
were already darkened before יום טוב *Yom Tov* began, so you knew
the water was already up in the clouds when יום טוב *Yom
Tov* was beginning. It wasn't on the ground and it wasn't קונה
שביתה koneh shvisah *koneh shevitah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: ודילמא
הני אזלי והני אחריני נינהו *v'dilma hanei azlei v'hanei achrinei ninhu*? So
okay, but how do you know that it was the dark clouds
that rained on יום טוב *Yom Tov*? Maybe those dark clouds blew
away and the rain came from other clouds from water that had
just recently evaporated? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: דאית להו סימנא
בגוייהו *d'it lehu simana b'gavaihu*. You have a סימן *siman* on it.
Like, you know, you wrote your name, you have a name tag
on the cloud, or something. Somehow, oh yeah, because it was the
cloud that looked like the bunny rabbit, so it's the same cloud.
Okay, ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'it eima*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* then has a
better answer: ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'it eima*, if you want I can say:
ספק דרבנן d'rabonon *safek d'rabbanan*. Okay, we don't know. Maybe it came
from the cloud that had already— that had already had the evaporated
water in it. Maybe it came from water that evaporated on יום
טוב *Yom Tov* itself. So it's a question about a rabbinic law
because this whole idea of תחומין *techumin* is rabbinic. וספק דרבנן d'rabbanans?
לקולא le-kula *v'safek d'rabbanan l'kula* and therefore you can be lenient. So
basically the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says maybe this water was on the
ground when יום טוב *Yom Tov* began. And says, oh, we don't
know, so it's a ספק *safek*, so it's ספק לקולא *safek l'kula*.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, let's assume it was
in the clouds when יום טוב *Yom Tov* began. וליקני שביתה בעבים
*v'likni shevitah b'avim*? Why it doesn't— why doesn't it establish שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbat* in the clouds? Why isn't that determinative of its תחום techum.
*techum*? So תיפשוט מינה *tifshot minah*, let's learn from there, right? דאין
תחומין למעלה מעשרה *d'ein techumin l'ma'ala m'asara*, that the reason we don't
say that it's— that it goes from two thousand אמה amos *amah*
from the clouds is because there's no תחומין *techumin* higher than ten
טפחים *tefachim*. וליקני שביתה בעבים *v'likni shevitah b'avim*, if there's תחומין *techumin*,
let it— let it sort of establish its place up in the
clouds. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, and this is better than
like אליהו *Eliyahu* descending from the clouds and the rain descending, etc.
So it says: לעולם אימא לך יש תחומין *le'olam eima lach yesh
techumin*. I will tell you really that we do do תחומין *techumin*
even not on the ground.
ומיא בעבי מיבלע בליעי *u'maya b'avei mivla blei'i*.
The water is absorbed in the clouds. It doesn't yet exist. So
therefore it doesn't exist before it rains, it's sort of seen as
part of the cloud, it's only vapor. So therefore there's no תחום
techum, *techum* for that water. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, and
now this is the question everybody was asking at the end of
yesterday: כל שכן דהוו להו נולד *kol sheken d'havu lehu nolad*. So
then it should certainly be a problem. Forget תחום *techum*, if it
doesn't really exist, it should be נולד *nolad*. דאסירי *d'assiri*? That it's
forbidden? אלא *Ela*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, fine, you're right. מיא
בעבי מידא ניידי *maya b'avei mida nayedi*. So the water— it's not
like it completely doesn't exist, like it's completely absorbed. It's there in
the cloud, but it's not stationary. You know, it's floating around as
water vapor, and therefore you don't have— you're not קונה שביתה koneh
shvisah *koneh shevitah* in something that is completely non-stationary. Now, by the
way, this idea that rain is not considered to be מוקצה *muktzeh*,
is not considered to be נולד *nolad*, is quite fascinating because in
general we go pretty crazy about what we consider to be נולד
*nolad*. Like we say like there's some opinions that basically if you
like, you know, make ice, that's נולד *nolad*, even though the water
was there and you're just like changing, you know, the state of
it, or or from ice to water is נולד *nolad*. And nevertheless,
you know, rain isn't מוקצה *muktzeh*, isn't נולד *nolad*, snow isn't נולד
*nolad*. So, I mean, which is okay, you can explain that, but
then we should have much more, you know, lax definitions of נולד
*nolad* in their— under other circumstances. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says it's not נולד *nolad* and it's not an issue about being
קונה שביתה *koneh shevitah* starting its place in the clouds because it's
moving, and moving you don't have a fixed space.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say you mean about
above ten טפחים *tefachim* you also have the fact that it's moving.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is essentially going to say that here,
right. And you're right, that actually is a good point, that would
be relevant therefore to a boat even within ten טפחים *tefachim* if
it's in the— if it's moving and hasn't docked. And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is essentially going to say that here about the— about
water.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: השתא דאתית להכי *hashta d'ateit l'hachi*,
now that you've come upon this answer, ודאוקיינוס נמי לא תיקשי לך
*v'd'Okyanus nami lo tikshei lach*.
Don't be bothered even assuming it started in the ocean, the water.
מיהא באוקיינוס נמי מיא ניידי *miha b'Okyanus nami maya nayedi*. The water
in the ocean is also moving. So now we have a new
idea that if something is moving when שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* begins, it's
not defined as establishing its place. דתניא *d'tanya*, and we taught in
a ברייתא Beraita, *braita*: נהרות המושכין ומעיינות הנובעים *neharot hamoshchin u'mayyanot hanovim*,
rivers that are— that are running and wells that are also, you
know, flowing, הרי הן כרגלי כל אדם *harei hen k'raglei kol adam*.
They do not go by where the water was when שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat* began, they go by where they are when you— when you
take the water out of them because they do not have— they
are not קונה שביתה *koneh shevitah*. They have no particular place for
שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, so they would only be defined once you took
possession of them. I should say in the case if you're on
the boat, you know, as Doug points out, bracketing the whole issue
of ten טפחים *tefachim*, if you're moving, it's not an issue, but
you're not קונה שביתה *koneh shevitah*, but presumably, you know, once you
stop, then it would be defined by where you stopped. Yes.
Well let's assume that it is ownerless and that's why it's like
הפקר. But as soon as you take possession of it, you draw
water from it on שבת, Shabbos then it becomes yours, and your
objects are defined by your תחום. Unless this has already established its
own תחום, which we're saying it would not, because it's not, it's
flowing. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, says like this. אמר רב
יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rav Yakov bar
Idi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, הלכה כרבי יוחנן בן נורי. halacha
k'Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. We rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri that if you are asleep, your שבת Shabbos begins
where you fell asleep and you have two thousand אמות amos and
you're not like somebody who was deposited חוץ לתחום chutz l'techum and
you only have four אמות. amos. אמר ליה רבי זירא לרב יעקב
בר אידי. Amar lei Rabbi Zeira l'Rav Yakov bar Idi. So רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira said to רב יעקב בר אידי, Rav Yakov bar
Idi, בפירוש שמיע לך, befeirush shemia lach, when you quoted this in
the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, did
he tell it to you explicitly? או מכללא שמיע לך, o m'chlala
shemia lach, or did you infer it from something he said? אמר
ליה בפירוש שמיע לי. Amar lei befeirush shemia li. No, I heard
it from him explicitly that we rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי.
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. So the גמרא Gemara says, now why do
you ask the question, did you infer it? Because מאי כללא, mai
klala, what would that other general statement have been that you might
have thought that he inferred it from that you bothered asking was
it inferred or said explicitly? Because here's a statement that רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi made. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב. D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi halacha k'divrei hameikel
b'eiruv. We rule like the lenient position in עירוב. eiruv. So he
said, maybe he didn't tell you explicitly we rule like רבי יוחנן
בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, but there's a general statement we
go by the lenient position in עירוב, eiruv, and therefore you inferred,
oh okay, so applying that here, that would mean we go like
רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. And he said no,
no, no, he might have made that general statement, but he also
said explicitly we rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri. Right, you realize why רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri is lenient, because according to חכמים Chachamim you only have four
אמות. amos. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says even
if you fell asleep, you have two thousand אמות amos in every
direction. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say, why did
he need to say both statements?
ותרוייהו למה לי, v'taryeihu lama li,
why did רב יעקב בר אידי Rav Yakov bar Idi say both
statements, we always go by the lenient position in עירוב eiruv and
he said we rule like רבי יוחנן
בן נורי? Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri? אמר רבי זירא צריכי. Amar Rabbi
Zeira tzrichi. Had to tell me both statements. דאי אשמעינן הלכה כרבי
יוחנן בן נורי, D'ei ashmeinan halacha k'Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, had he
just said we rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri, הוה אמינא בין לקולא בין לחומרא, hava amina bein l'kula bein
l'chumra, even maybe even when רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri is strict. When would רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri be strict? Remember the גמרא Gemara before said that רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri might be based on the position
that inanimate objects are קונה שביתה where they begin שבת Shabbos. or
יום טוב, right? And the sleeping person is like the inanimate object.
But that generally is a strict position, because that means they're limited
from a two thousand אמות amos radius of where they began שבת
as opposed to the more lenient position that says that an inanimate
object is defined by the person who finds it. Well if I
found the object, I want to be able to carry it within
the space that I can go, I don't want it to be
defined by some different zone. So רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so the
רבי יוחנן בן נורי'ס Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri's idea applied to inanimate
objects would actually be a stringency. So had he just said we
rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, you would
have said not only by sleeping people but even by inanimate objects,
even לחומרא. l'chumra. קא משמע לן הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב. Ka mashma
lan halacha k'divrei hameikel b'eiruv. So they're saying we go lenient both
ways. By a sleeping person we go like רבי יוחנן בן נורי,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, and it's where you fell asleep two thousand
אמות amos rather than four אמות. amos. And by an inanimate object,
it doesn't start שבת where it began, it's based on the person
who finds it. Now רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos are both bothered,
because you remember actually in this מסכת masechet towards the way earlier
we said that you can't go by two contradictory קולא kula positions,
right? So make up your mind. Either you פסקן pasken inanimate objects
are defined by where they begin, or you פסקן pasken they're not.
How can you be פסקן pasken the lenient position both ways? By
a person we'll say it does begin where it starts, by an
object we'll say it won't. Okay, so רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
both say this in this statement the גמרא Gemara is going back
to what it suggested yesterday, that רבי יוחנן בן נורי'ס Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri's position is not based on the idea of inanimate objects.
רבי יוחנן בן נורי'ס Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri's position is that because
since you're a person,
were you awake שבת you would be קונה שביתה where you are,
even when you're asleep it works. But if you're an inanimate object,
oh that's categorically different. There maybe even רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri would say it is not defined, you know, where
it starts שבת. Okay, so it's not necessarily a contradictory פסק. psak.
So we're lenient both ways. For the person we say he is
defined where he is, where he was, even when he was asleep,
but for an object, not. An object is defined by the person
who finds it. Okay, so that's why he has to tell me
הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב halacha k'divrei hameikel b'eiruv
and not straight
רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. אלא ולימא הלכה כדברי
המיקל בעירוב, Ela v'leima halacha k'divrei hameikel b'eiruv, just say that we
always take the lenient position by עירוב. eiruv. הלכה כרבי יוחנן בן
נורי למה לי, Halacha k'Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri lama li, why did
you bother saying we rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי? Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri? Right, we could have just figured out, oh we go
by the lenient position, so here by the guy falling asleep, we'll
say that like רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. No,
איצטריך. itztrich. You needed to tell me explicitly we go by רבי
יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach
amina, I would have thought to say הני מילי, hani mili, when
is it true you go by the lenient
position, יחיד במקום יחיד ורבים במקום רבים, yachid b'makom yachid v'rabim b'makom
rabim, if
it is... But if it's one against many like רבי יוחנן בן
נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is up against the חכמים Chachamim which
presumably is multiple opinions. So אימא לא, eima lo, maybe this rule
of going by the lenient opinion would not apply. So therefore he
had to tell me no, it even applies to this case and
we go like רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. Okay
so now that's all very fascinating but it also is very it
has a broad relevance outside of this case. It says that for
all of הלכות עירובין hilchos eruvin pretty much everything we're going to
be learning we pretty much always adopt the lenient position even in
an un- even in an uneven fight. You know even in a
you know one against many we always go by the lenient position.
We're going to see at the bottom of the דף daf there's
one other place where you know or or one other you know
significantly other place in which we say this as well which we
always adopt the lenient position maybe even if it's you know an
uneven fight and that's by אבילות. aveilus. We say הלכה כדברי המיקל
באבל. Halacha k'divrei hameikel b'avel. Okay and הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב. Halacha
k'divrei hameikel b'eruv. And what this גמרא Gemara is saying is that's
not just because we say oh it's דרבנן derabbanan so we'll be
מיקל. meikel. It's even in a case where where normal rules would
tell you to be מחמיר machmir like one against many and you
would normally rule like the majority. Okay and that's what we're saying
here and that's why he pointed it out even in the case
of רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri even one against
many. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to develop exactly that point.
Let's take a look. אמר ליה
רבא לאביי.
Amar lei
Rava l'Abaye. So רבא Rava said to אביי. Abaye. Okay. נחתי. Neichtai.
One minute. Let's take a look here. עירובין דרבנן. Eruvin d'rabonon. So
עירובין eruvin is rabbinic. מה לי יחיד במקום יחיד מה לי יחיד
במקום רבים. Mah li yachid bimkom yachid mah li yachid bimkom rabim.
He didn't think this was a חידוש. chidush. If it's rabbinic you
should always be lenient even one against many. Okay which is a
fascinating idea. So the other so here רב פפא Rav Papa is
going to correct him. אמר ליה רבא Amar lei Rava so רב
פפא Rav Papa said back to him excuse me to רבא. Rava.
ובדרבנן לא שני לן בין יחיד במקום יחיד ליחיד במקום רבים? U'vidrabonon
lo shani lan bein yachid bimkom yachid l'yachid bimkom rabim? You mean
to say that you think in rabbinic matters it doesn't matter one
against one and one against many? We're always lenient in all rabbinic
matters? It's not a special thing here by עירוב? eruv? והתנן, V'ha
tnan, we talk- I'll give you an example, we turn the משנה.
Mishna. רבי אליעזר אומר כל אשה שעברו עליה שלשה עונות. Rabbi Eliezer
omer kol isha she'avrah aleiha shlosha onot. This is by נדה. niddah.
And by נדה niddah there's a position- a question about the status
of a woman who's hit menopause. זקנה. Zakeinah. An elderly woman is
the halachic definition, how you define that whatever and then it says
once that woman is old and she goes three periods 90 days
without having her period without without bleeding, she is considered to be
מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. Somebody who is blood is you know no
longer- she's no longer a woman that would normally get her period.
And that has various relevance for הלכות halachos that you don't have
to be concerned that she's bled even if even if she bleeds
you don't have to be concerned that you know she might have
been bleeding earlier you assume it's only when she actually saw it
because in general you assume because this has a lot of relevance
not just for נדה niddah as we practice it you know for
husband and wife having sex it has relevance for if she handled
תרומה trumah when do you assume she became טמא. tamei. So if
you're in a status of מסולקת דמים, mesuleket damim, removed of blood,
you basically have none of those concerns. So when is that? That's
if she went- she was older and I knew that was going
to happen she was older it's okay it's okay and she went
90 days without bleeding. Now then there's the position of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer who said even if she's not old any woman who
went 90 days without bleeding gets into that category.
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says
so the גמרא Gemara, I'm sorry so the גמרא Gemara it's one
of those days so the גמרא Gemara oh you got some tape
there oh good man. Okay so the גמרא gemara. says
okay that's going to fall again. So the okay where are we?
There we go. So thank you. So the גמרא gemara says like
this. So the גמרא gemara says והתנן v'hatnan רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says כל אשה שעברו עליה שלשה
עונות, kol isha she'avrah aleiha shlosha onot,
any woman who any woman not only an older woman who thir-
three periods 90 days went, דיה שעתה, dayah shaatah, she finds blood
she can assume it happened just now and she doesn't have to
be concerned that she had bled earlier. Okay. ותניא, V'tanya, so that's
a lenient position and that's thank you יחיד במקום רבים yachid bimkom
rabim because he's a single opinion against the majority position of the
חכמים. Chachamim. ותניא, V'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Baraisa: מעשה ועשה
רבי כרבי אליעזר. maaseh v'asah Rabbi k'Rabbi Eliezer. There was a case
that רבי Rabbi ruled like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. A woman had-
was not older but she went three- three months without bleeding and
she had handled some תרומה trumah and he said no problem. He
ruled like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. לאחר שנזכר, L'achar shenizkar,
after he remembered, we'll see in a minute what he remembered, אמר,
oh, כדאי הוא רבי אליעזר לסמוך עליו בשעת הדחק. kedai hu Rabbi
Eliezer lismoch alav b'shat hadachak. We can rely on רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer even though he's a דעת יחיד, daas yachid, we can rely
on him because it was a case of exigency. רש"י Rashi says
it was a period of famine. Actually if it's a period of
famine you understand maybe why she didn't have her period right because
malnutrition is a reason for why women start getting their period anyway.
So therefore תוספות Tosafos just says that she had handled a lot
of תרומה trumah and it would have been a very big loss.
Okay so that's an important position about relying on a דעת יחיד.
daas yachid. הכי בשעת הדחק, hachi b'sha'as hadechak, very important halachic position,
that today's דף daf really beyond its local discussions about עירוב eruv
are very important in terms of
פסק psak parameters. Rebbe said, he was a דעת יחיד da'as yachid
but we could rely on him בשעת הדחק. b'sha'as hadechak. מה לאחר
שנזכר? ma l'achar shenizkar? What does it mean he remembered? What did
he remember he did wrong? What was he thinking and why was
he disturbed? אילימא לאחר שנזכר דאין הלכה כרבי אליעזר, ileima l'achar shenizkar
d'ein halakha k'Rebbe Eliezer,
maybe he remembered that the הלכה halakha is not like Rabbi Eliezer,
אלא כרבנן, ela k'Rabbanan, but rather like the רבנן. Rabbanan. So בשעת
הדחק היכי עביד כוותיה? b'sha'as hadechak heichi avid k'vasei? How did he
rule like him בשעת הדחק? b'sha'as hadechak? He stops being a דעת
יחיד. da'as yachid. Now this is a very important question in הלכה.
halakha. We say you can rule like a דעת יחיד da'as yachid
בשעת הדחק. b'sha'as hadechak. First of all there's questions: does that mean
only on דרבנן? derabbanan, Can we even rule like a דעת יחיד
da'as yachid on דאורייתא d'oraisas בשעת הדחק? b'sha'as hadechak? But the other
very important question is, what constitutes a דעת יחיד? da'as yachid? And
that's question in two ways. Number one is: let's say some weird
guy you never heard of once said this idea. Is that a
דעת יחיד? da'as yachid? How weighty does the position have to be?
But then there's another question: even if it started off as a
weighty position, when does it completely—when does it stop being an active
position? When has פסק psak basically said this no longer exists as
even a minority position? So there are some—this actually is related to
the question of the canonization of the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. You
realize when the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch first came out, it was
one opinion among many and it was over a period of time
that it became more and more authoritative. So one of the areas
where you see this is a question of: can you rule like
a שיטה shita in the ראשונים Rishonim if it's not in the
שולחן ערוך? Shulchan Aruch? Does it continue to be a דעת יחיד?
da'as yachid? So this is a very important question: at what time
is it something considered to be—this stops being a voice? So that's
what the גמרא gemara says. If we had ruled explicitly like the
רבנן, Rabbanan, you would never be able to use Rabbi Eliezer, even
בשעת הדחק. b'sha'as hadechak. One minute. So therefore, what was his issue?
Why was he thinking 'I should have gone like the Rabbis but
I can rely on Rabbi Eliezer'? So it says,
אלא דלא איתמר הלכתא לא כרבי אליעזר ולא כרבנן. ela d'lo itmar
hilchesa lo k'Rabbi Eliezer v'lo k'Rabbanan. We hadn't explicitly ruled either way.
But לאחר שנזכר, l'achar shenizkar, so what did he remember and that
he had done wrong or made a mistake? דלאו יחיד פליג עליה
אלא רבים פליגי עליה. d'lav yachid palig alei ela rabbim paligi alei.
He realized: look, we hadn't explicitly ruled, but the normal
rules of פסק psak should have made me rule like the Rabbis
because it's a many—it's the רבים, rabbim, they're the majority against a
single opinion. So it's not like Rabbi Eliezer's position has been completely
rejected, but normal פסק psak rules I should have ruled like the
Rabbis. Nevertheless,
אמר כדאי רבי אליעזר לסמוך עליו בשעת הדחק. amar k'dai Rabbi Eliezer
lismoch alav b'sha'as hadechak. I can rely on Rabbi Eliezer because it
is a שעת הדחק. sha'as hadechak. So this becomes a very important
principle that if a דעת יחיד da'as yachid is not
completely silenced, if it's not like we absolutely ruled this way and
the other position is completely rejected, if it's not seen as completely
silenced, then בשעת הדחק b'sha'as hadechak
you can rely on it. There are these questions I said: is
it only in rabbinic matters or even in biblical matters? There's a
lot of literature about what are those parameters. רב קוק Rav Kook
has a long discussion about it in his whole introduction to שבת
הארץ, Shabbos Aretz, his book about שמיטה, Shemitah, because in his introduction
he lays the groundwork for the whole idea of היתר מכירה Heter
Mechirah and he wants to say, can you rely on the various
שיטות shitos that we can do מכירה mechirah of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael בזמן הזה b'zman hazeh that it'll work to deal with issues
of שמיטה Shemitah etc.? And he has a whole discussion of the
parameters of relying on a דעת יחיד da'as yachid בשעת הדחק. b'sha'as
hadechak. So in terms of this גמרא, gemara the argument was: look,
you see that even by rabbinic matters like this issue was,
that if it's many against one you rule like the many. Right?
We don't say if it's rabbinic matters we normally always go by
every lenient opinion. We would rule by the majority over a single
opinion. So it really is a חידוש chidush to say that by
עירובין Eruvin we're going to rule like a minority opinion even in
the face of many. Yes, Charlie?
But two issues: one,
what about when the
שולחן ערוך—this Shulchan Aruch goes to your application—when the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch goes by a minority opinion in the ראשונים? Rishonim? Second, what
if there's a ראשון Rishon the author of the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch didn't even know about, such as the מאירי?
Meiri? Right. Those are all good questions which I'm not going to
answer. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Yes, Bob?
Who determines what's a שעת הדחק sha'as hadechak and when does it
stop and then does it ever revert back?
That's a good point. Who determines what's a
שעת הדחק? sha'as hadechak? That's the responsibility of every rabbi and that's
why it matters which פוסק posek you go to because it's not
a science, it's an art and there's a lot of judgments and
all these issues: is this still considered a legitimate דעת יחיד? da'as
yachid? Or does it stop being a דעת יחיד? da'as yachid? Is
this a legitimate שעת הדחק? sha'as hadechak? All of those are judgment
calls that the פוסק posek makes. I mean obviously informed by precedent
and literature and so on, but ultimately there's contradictory... evidence around all
of this, and it's all and it's going to be a lot
of this is going to be a judgment call. The second question
you ask is an excellent one, which is, yes, there's a difference
between having sort of the black letter law and then understanding a
latitude that you have in exceptional cases and as opposed to changing
the codified law. You know, so if you say yes, really the
law is X, but there are other opinions out there that you
can rely on בשעת הדחק b'sha'as hadchak is a very different type
of a move than saying we're actually going to, you know, change
the law based on those opinions, which is those that don't like
היתר מכירה, heter mechira, you know, that's, you know, some that's one
of their arguments. They say, well, רב קוק Rav Kook only said
it was because of שעת הדחק. sha'as hadchak. So if we say
it's no longer a שעת הדחק sha'as hadchak it goes back to
saying we shouldn't rely on those positions. All right, so anyway, let's
take a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב משורשיא
בריה דרב פפא. Amar Rav Mesharshia brei d'Rav Papa. So רב משורשיא
Rav Mesharshia said again back to רבא Rava who said, oh, what's
the חידוש? chiddush? And everything what do you mean? It's a big
חידוש chiddush that normally even by rabbinic matters you would go by
the majority. So he's going to say the same thing. ואי תימא
רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא, V'ei teima Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak l'Rava,
or some say רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said
to רבא, Rava, מדדרבנן לא שני בין יחיד במקום יחיד יחיד במקום
רבים, mid'derabbanan lo shani bein yachid b'makom yachid yachid b'makom rabbim, you
think it doesn't matter by all rabbinic laws that we would go
by the, you know, by the lenient even a minor a single
opinion against a majority? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we learned in a ברייתא: Baraisa,
שמועה קרובה, Shemua kerova, somebody hears that a relative, an immediate relative
passed away and they hear it in the recent aftermath, which he
means within thirty days of the death, נוהג שבעה ושלושים, noheig shiva
u'sheloshim, that person does the מנהגים minhagim of שבעה shiva and the
שלושים. sheloshim. ורחוקה, U'rechoka, if it was a if they heard about
it a long time later, which is after thirty days, אינו נוהג
אלא יום אחד, eino noheig ela yom echad, there's only one day
of אבילות aveilus that that person keeps. ואיזו היא קרובה ואיזו היא
רחוקה, V'eizo hi kerova v'eizo hi rechoka, what's the difference between near
and far, you know, recent and and far in the past? בתוך
שלושים קרובה, Betoch sheloshim kerova, within thirty days is near, לאחר שלושים
רחוקה, le-achar sheloshim rechoka, after is far. דברי רבי עקיבא, Divrei Rabbi
Akiva, that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position. וחכמים אומרים, Ve-chachamim omrim, and
the sages say: אחד שמועה קרובה ואחד שמועה רחוקה, echad shemua kerova
v'echad shemua rechoka, whether it's a recent report or an old report,
נוהג שבעה ושלושים. noheig shiva u'sheloshim. You do שבעה ושלושים. shiva u'sheloshim.
So again, it's a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva against a majority opinion.
And what's the פסק? psak? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן: Ve-amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan: כל מקום שאתה
מוצא יחיד מקל ורבים מחמירים, kol makom she-ata motzei yachid meikel v'rabbim
machmirim, whenever you find an individual that's מקל meikel and a majority
that's מחמיר, machmir, הלכה כדברי המחמירים, halacha k'divrei hamachmirim, you go by
the majority. It would have been interesting to hear him say the
opposite, right, that even if the מחמירים machmirim are מקל, meikel, but
anyway the general rule is we go, but maybe the point is
even though it's דרבנן derabbanan. and we would normally maybe go by
the lenient position, you go by the majority position even if they're
the מחמיר machmir one. כדברי המחמירים המרובים. K'divrei hamachmirim hamerubim. חוץ מזו,
Chutz mizo, this case of שמועה קרובה shemua kerova is an exception
שאף על פי שרבי עקיבא מקל וחכמים מחמירים, she-af al pi she-Rabbi
Akiva meikel va-Chachamim machmirim, even though רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva lenient and
the Rabbis are מחמיר machmir and they're the majority opinion, הלכה כדברי
רבי עקיבא, halacha k'divrei Rabbi Akiva, we go like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. Now why is that? Why is it violating the rule that
we're going by a דעת יחיד? da'as yachid? וסבר לה כשמואל, Ve-savar
lah k'Shmuel, he holds like שמואל, Shmuel,
דאמר שמואל הלכה כדברי המקל באבל, d'amar Shmuel halacha k'divrei hameikel b'avel,
by אבילות aveilus we go like the lenient position. באבל הוא דאקילו
רבנן, B'avel hu d'akilu rabbanan, by אבילות aveilus is when the Rabbis
were lenient. It's a special exception. אבל בעלמא, Aval b'alma, but the
normal rule we see being expressed in this ברייתא, Baraisa this ברייתא
said what to the normal rule should have been: you go like
the majority. אפילו בדרבנן, Afilu b'derabbanan, even by rabbinic law, שני בין
יחיד במקום יחיד יחיד במקום רבים. shani bein yachid b'makom yachid yachid
b'makom rabbim. It makes a difference whether it's one against one or
one against many. So this basically is a very important גמרא Gemara
and it basically said the following: there's an idea that you go
by the lenient position by דרבנן, de-rabbanan, okay, but the general rule
would be that's all other things being equal. First of all, if
you if you, you know, learn the סוגיא sugya and you're persuaded
that one position is right, you פסקן pasken that way. But let's
say there's equal that, you know, you don't know how to פסקן,
pasken, so then okay you go by the lenient position. But that's
only if other things are equal. If it's minority position against majority,
you would rule like the majority. That's the general rule by דרבנן.
There are two exceptions to it: הלכה כדברי המקל בעירוב halacha k'divrei
hameikel b'eiruv and הלכה כדברי המקל באבל. halacha k'divrei hameikel b'avel. And
in עירובין eiruvin and אבילות, aveilus, quite interesting, right, those two big
areas the, you know, based on the גמרא Gemara it's not exactly
clear why those are such exceptions, but those areas are ones in
which we always adopt the lenient position even presumably it's one against
many, and that is the חידוש chiddush that is being said here.
Okay, so now let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
Yeah. And of course remember that important point about, you know, that
we also said in passing that even when you פסקן pasken like
the majority, if a certain position has not completely been rejected then,
you know, you can be סומך someich on it בשעת הדחק, b'sha'as
hadchak, which is a really regular and critical part of פסקנינג paskening
הלכה. halacha. Yes.
I have a friend who was adopted and her father died, and
they didn't let her sit שבעה shiva or anything.
Yeah, that's a different issue. That's not שמועה קרובה shemua kerova or
רחוקה. rechoka. That has to do with, you know, whether you sit
שבעה shiva for an adoptive parent because it's not biological parent and
so on. That's a separate conversation. Right.
OK.
Just if there's a...
Well,
that's an issue because when you say מקיל makeil for some people,
what, meaning to make it, it would be easier for them if
you would let them sit שבעה, shiva, you know, so that's an
interesting סברא sevara how you define מקיל makeil by אבילות, aveilus, you
know, it's defined as demanding less of you, but you know, but
what about allowing you? And there actually look, most I would say
sympathetic פוסקים poskim will say that even if you're not technically חייב
chayav to sit for an adoptive parent that you're allowed to sit
or they, you know, make certain ways to make a distinction between
the normal sitting of שבעה shiva but basically so that's also, you
know, the most מקיל makeil is to give you the option, you
know, to if you think about it that way, yeah. That's a
good question. All right. So anyway, so let's take a look as
the גמרא Gemara continues. ורב פפא אמר, VeRav Pappa amar, now back
to this question, so that was all one approach. Why did you
need to tell me we rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי? Reb
Yochanan ben Nuri? Because even though it was, even though it was
עירוב eiruv and דרבנן, he was a יחיד במקום רבים. yachid bimkom
rabbim. ורב פפא אמר אצטריך. VeRav Pappa amar itztarich. You needed to
tell me both things. We go לקולא all the time and we
rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Reb Yochanan ben Nuri. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought הני מילי hani mili
בערב חצירות. be-eiruv chatzeiros. Maybe when are we lenient by עירוב? eiruv?
By עירוב חצירות. eiruv chatzeiros. אבל בעירובי תחומין, Aval be-eiruvi techumin, אימא
לא, eima lo, maybe we wouldn't, maybe this rule you're always lenient
wouldn't apply to עירובי תחומין. eiruvi techumin. צריכא, Tzericha, you need to
tell me both. ומנא תימרא דשאני לן בין עירוב חצירות ועירוב תחומין?
U-mena teimra de-shani lan bein eiruv chatzeiros ve-eiruv techumin? What would have
let me think that there would have been a difference? Now the
easiest thing to say is that עירובי תחומין eiruvi techumin are connected
to a דאורייתא de-oraisa concept, right? You know, according to some there's
an aspect of it that's דאורייתא. de-oraisa. But that's not what the
גמרא Gemara says. דתנן. De-tenan. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, במה
דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim בעירובי תחומין? be-eiruvi techumin? When is it
that you can not do an עירוב eiruv for somebody? By עירובי
תחומין. eiruvi techumin. I can't go say, oh, oh, I'm going to
be nice, I'm going to make Charlie's עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumin, you
know, two thousand אמה out the city. Obviously I can't do that.
Who says Charlie, that means that Charlie can travel more in that
direction but less in the other direction. So I can't do it
on his behalf without his knowledge. It's hurting him. So when is
it true? That's true about עירובי תחומין. eiruvi techumin. אבל בעירובי חצירות,
Aval be-eiruvi chatzeiros, if Charlie and I are all part of a
courtyard here and we want to do an עירוב חצירות eiruv chatzeiros
to carry in the courtyard and Charlie isn't around, so I can,
you know, do it on Charlie's behalf here, it's only to his
benefit. אבל בעירובי חצירות מערבין בין לדעת בין שלא לדעת. Aval be-eiruvi
chatzeiros me-arvin bein le-daas bein she-lo le-daas. You can do it whether
he's aware or not aware. שזכין לאדם שלא בפניו. She-zakin le-adam she-lo
be-fanav. You can merit for somebody not in his presence. You can
do them good even without their knowledge and acquiescence. ואין חבין לאדם,
Ve-ein chavin le-adam, but you can't do something that has a sort
of, you know, a negative impact on somebody, even if it's not
all negative, even if only one aspect is negative, אלא בפניו, ela
be-fanav, only in their presence, only with their knowledge and agreement. So
I can't set the עירוב תחומין eiruv techumin unless he agrees and
is aware. Now the point is, as תוספות Tosafos says, that's not
because עירובי תחומין eiruvi techumin is more מחמיר. machmir. That's just because
of the realities that עירובי תחומין eiruvi techumin has with it, you
know, a trade-off that עירובי חצירות eiruvi chatzeiros does not have. So
תוספות Tosafos says, you know what, but there really are trade-offs in
both directions. First of all, what this means is even if I
overheard Charlie saying, oh, I'm really looking forward to, you know, going
to greet my רבי rebe when he comes out, you know, from
the east, that even then I can't do it without him knowing
because since there is some loss, even if I know that basically
he's interested in it, I need his explicit acquiescence and agreement. So
תוספות Tosafos says, but you know, there's some loss in the עירוב
חצירות eiruv chatzeiros case as well because I'm actually going into his
house and taking some of his bread and using that to contribute
to make the עירוב. eiruv. So in תוספות' Tosafos view, in both
cases there's a gain and a loss and the fact that we
let me do it by עירוב חצירות eiruv chatzeiros and we don't
let me do it by עירובי תחומין eiruvi techumin shows that we
are more lenient by עירוב חצירות. eiruv chatzeiros. That's how תוספות Tosafos
reads it. It is a funny proof in the גמרא, Gemara could
have just said עירובי תחומין eiruvi techumin has a דאורייתא de-oraisa component.
Anyway, that's why רב פפא Rav Pappa says you needed to say
we go like רבי יוחנן בן נורי Reb Yochanan ben Nuri to
emphasize that we're lenient by עירוב eiruv even by עירובי תחומין. eiruvi
techumin. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara goes on. ורב אשי אמר
אצטריך. Ve-Rav Ashi amar itztarich. I needed you to tell me we
rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי Reb Yochanan ben Nuri for the
following
reason. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought הני
מילי בשיורי עירוב. hani mili be-shiyurei eiruv. When is it that we're
lenient by עירוב, eiruv, maybe by the remnant of an עירוב, eiruv,
meaning that the עירוב eiruv was good and the question is does
it remain good. אבל בתחילת עירוב, Aval bi-techillas eiruv, if it's a
question at the outset should I rule it to be a good
עירוב, eiruv, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe we wouldn't be so lenient.
ומנא תימרא U-mena teimra says the גמרא דשאני לן בין שיורי עירוב
לבין תחילת עירוב? de-shani lan bein shiyurei eiruv le-vein techillas eiruv? Why
would I have thought that you might have been more lenient by
the remnant of an עירוב, eiruv, the after it was placed, rather
than before it was placed? דתנן, De-tenan, because we learned in a
משנה, Mishnah, אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, במה דברים אמורים בתחילת
עירוב? bameh devarim amurim bi-techillas eiruv? When is it that you have
a minimum amount of food that has to be contributed when you're
first putting down the עירוב? eiruv? אבל בשיורי עירוב, Aval be-shiyurei eiruv,
if you made a good עירוב eiruv and then the food got,
you know, eaten away or something happened to it and there was
only a tiny little bit left, so once you're dealing with after
it was already good, אפילו כל שהוא, afilu kol she-hu, even a
small amount. So you see you're more lenient once it was good
than you are at the outset. ולא אמרו לערב חצרות אלא כדי
שלא לשכוח תורת עירוב מן התינוקות v'lo amru l'arev chatzeros ella k'dei
shelo lishkach toras eruv min hatinokos and the only reason they said
to do עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeros was that the children should not
forget עירוב, eruv, should not forget. Now what does that mean? Forget
what? I mean, what do you mean the only reason they said?
So there's a whole question what this means, but the simple explanation
is, is that it's talking about a particular case where here's your
alleyway, and you have, right, you have like, you know, three separate
courtyards opening into the alleyway. So normally each courtyard would make their
own עירוב, eruv, and then they all make a שיתוף מבואות shituf
mavo'os in the alleyway. But what happens if these courtyards also fed
one into the other? They had side doors, right, yeah, like that
picture, and they also all made an עירוב eruv together. So once
they're all making an עירוב eruv together, they don't actually really have
to make a שיתוף מבואות shituf mavo'os in the alleyway as well.
So that's what he's saying, yes, it's true, in this case they
really wouldn't have to do it, but it's שלא לשכוח תורת עירוב
מן התינוקות. shelo lishkach toras eruv min hatinokos. So we don't want
to forget, and therefore in this case we demand it. So it's
really a parenthetical statement. Anyway, the point being is I might have
thought to apply it after the עירוב eruv was good and not
say you're always lenient before the עירוב eruv was good because we
might make a difference, a distinction.
What distinction it says you teach them the wrong thing. These children.
No, you don't teach them the wrong thing. No, no, no, yeah,
but you know there's a question about חינוך chinuch and habituation, that,
you know, and it's not only about children, you know, we sort
of, based on what we've done in the past, we make, you
know, we infer certain things, and they might be correct or incorrect
inference. So if we saw that all the courtyards were carrying in
this alleyway and they didn't do a שיתוף מבואות, shituf mavo'os, I
might infer you never need to do a שיתוף מבואות. shituf mavo'os.
So it makes more sense to always demand a שיתוף מבואות shituf
mavo'os even in some cases where technically it might not be, because,
you know, it's also a question of which misinference is more consequential,
is more potentially problematic. So to think I always need it is
not as bad as thinking I never need it. Okay, let's see,
let's continue in the גמרא.
רבי יעקב רבי זריקא אמרו. Rabbi Yaakov Rabbi Zrika amru. So this
is quite a fascinating digression in the גמרא talking about general principles
of
פסק. psak. יחיד במקום רבים, yachid bimkom rabbim, כדאי הוא דעת יחיד
בשעת הדחק, kedai hu das yachid bishas hadchak, הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב,
halacha k'divrei hameikel b'eruv, הלכה כדברי המיקל באבל. halacha k'divrei hameikel b'avel.
And now we're going to get to a section of the גמרא
which is what is the rules when different תנאים tanna'im argue with
one another. Are there positions we favor one over the other as
a general rule? Okay, so here it is. רבי יעקב ורבי זריקא
אמרו הלכה כרבי עקיבא מחבירו, Rabbi Yaakov v'Rabbi Zrika amru halacha k'rabbi
akiva mechavero, we'll always rule like רבי עקיבא rabbi akiva when he
argues with a single opinion, his friend, but not his friends, if
it's many against one we won't. וכרבי יוסי מחבריו, u'k'rabbi yose mechaverav,
and we'll rule like רבי יוסי rabbi yose even if he disagrees
with multiple opinions. וכרבי מחבירו, u'k'rebbi mechavero, and we'll rule like רבי,
rebbi, רבי יהודה הנשיא, rabbi yehuda hanasi, against a single opinion, his
colleague but not colleagues. Okay, so these are general כללי פסק. klalei
psak. So the גמרא says, למאי הלכתא? l'mai hilchsa? Now for what
purpose are you telling me we rule like
them, meaning are you saying we absolutely rule like it, you know,
blindly,
100%? So רבי יוחנן אמר הלכה. Rabbi Yochanan amar halacha. Yes, we
fully rule like it, הלכה. halacha. רבי חייא בר אבא אמר מטים,
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar matim, we incline that way. רבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא אמר נראים, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina amar nir'im, it seems
to us that position. Now what's the difference between incline and seems?
So רש״י rashi says one thing, I'll tell you what תוספות tosafos
says which makes I think a little bit more sense. תוספות tosafos
says to say we absolutely rule that way, remember like in the
גמרא before, if it said הלכה, halacha, then the other opinion even
stops being a דעת יחיד. das yachid. So if we say הלכה
halacha like from רבי עקיבא מחבירו, rabbi akiva mechavero, that means if
somebody ruled like the opposing position, you would actually have to reverse
the פסק. psak. The other position becomes completely illegitimate. מטים matim means,
yes, I'll rule like רבי עקיבא, rabbi akiva, but the other position
remains a legitimate דעת יחיד. das yachid. And therefore if somebody ruled
like it, it's a legitimate rule. נראים nir'im is even weaker. נראים
nir'im means, you know, this opinion appears more correct, so it should
be the one that you should go by, but it's completely legitimate
to rule even לכתחילה l'chatchila like the other position. So different degrees
about how much we're saying this is the absolute or, you know,
this is the weightier position. Okay, so that's quite fascinating those three
things on a hierarchy of how much does it mean to לפסוק
pasken like one position over the other.
What was the first one? First one?
הלכה, halacha, which means that the other position is completely illegitimate. Okay,
מטים matim means the other one is legitimate maybe בדיעבד, bedieved, בשעת
הדחק, b'shas hadchak, and נראים nir'im means it's really, you know, it
seems more correct to לפסוק pasken one way but it's completely legitimate
to לפסוק pasken the other way as well. All right, so three
different interpretations of what it means we rule like this one over
that one. Okay, כלשון זה אמר
רבי
יעקב בר אידי. kloshan zeh amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi. So רבי
יעקב בר אידי Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi had the following way of
saying over different ideas, different rules of how you לפסוק. pasken. אמר
רבי יוחנן רבי מאיר רבי יהודה Amar Rabbi Yochanan Rabbi Meir Rabbi
Yehuda so he said in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda if it's a
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda הלכה
רבי יהודה. Halakha Rabbi Yehuda. We go like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי Rabbi Yehuda v’Rabbi Yose if it's רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda against רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose remember רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
was the one that we ruled even against multiple multiple opposing positions
הלכה רבי יוסי. Halakha Rabbi Yose. We go like רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is you know beats רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose beats רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
so therefore פשיטא? pshita? No. So therefore אין צריך לומר ein tzorich
lomar you don't have to tell me רבי מאיר ורבי יוסי הלכה
רבי יוסי Rabbi Meir v’Rabbi Yose Halakha Rabbi Yose that רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose beats out רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir as a transitive axiom
of inequality. Okay השתא במקום רבי יהודה ליתא hashta b’makom Rabbi Yehuda
leisa if רבי מאיר’s Rabbi Meir position is rejected in the presence
of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda במקום רבי יוסי מיבעיא b’makom Rabbi Yose mibaya
would there be any question? Okay אמר רב אסי Amar Rav Assi
said רב אסי Rav Assi אף אני לומד. Af ani lomed. So
if we're talking about כללי פסק klalei psak I'll tell you the
principles I
use. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yose v’Rabbi Shimon if it's רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose who is a very weighty one we heard against
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon הלכה רבי יוסי. Halakha Rabbi Yose. We go
like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. דאמר רב אבא אמר רב יוחנן d'amar
Rav Abba amar Rav Yochanan רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yehuda v’Rabbi
Shimon how do I know this? Because I figured out from the
following because we teach that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda versus רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon הלכה רבי יהודה. Halakha Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
wins out. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda beats רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
and we know that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose beats רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda so השתא במקום רבי יהודה ליתא hashta b’makom Rabbi Yehuda leisa
if רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position is rejected in the presence of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda במקום רבי יוסי מיבעיא b’makom Rabbi Yose mibaya
is there any question about what it is when he beats up
when he's against רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose? So clearly using this transitive
axiom we know that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose beats out רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda beats out two positions the
weakest two positions that have been put on this list are רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So now the גמרא
says איבעיא להו ibaia lehu they asked רבי מאיר ורבי שמעון Rabbi
Meir v’Rabbi Shimon let's say it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir against רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon מאי mai what would we say? תיקו teiku that's
what we know. We don't know. Now the גמרא begins to challenge
this idea that we always go by what by the following lineup
by these rules always apply and it's going to say what are
you talking about there are times we פוסקין poskin you know one
of these against the other. So we'll read one example about this
and we'll stop with that for today. So the גמרא says like
this אמר רב
משארשיא Amar Rav Mesharshiya said רב משארשיא Rav Mesharshiya ליתנהו להני כללי.
leisnehu l’hanei klalei. We don't hold of these rules. מנא ליה לרב
משארשיא הא Mina leh l’Rav Mesharshiya ha where does רב משארשיא Rav
Mesharshiya get that that these rules are really not how we פוסקין
poskin by? אילימא מהא דתנן Ilima meha d’tenan because we taught in
the משנה Mishnah רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer based on our
משנה Mishnah למה הדבר דומה l’ma hadavar domeh what is this case
like when you know people's four אמות amot overlap with one another?
לג' חצרות הפתוחות לזו ופתוחות לרשות הרבים l'gimmel chatzeirot hapetuchot lazo u'petuchot
l'reshut harabim the three courtyards that they open to one another and
they open to the street. עירבו שתיהן החיצונות עם האמצעית Eirvu shteihen
hachitzonot im haemtzait if one and two made an עירוב eiruv and
two and three made an עירוב eiruv then you know there's everybody
overlaps in two. היא מותרת עמהן Hi muteret imahen so two can
carry with one and three. והן מותרות עמה v’hen mutarot ima one
and three can carry with two. ושתיהן החיצונות אסורות זו עם זו
U’shteihen hachitzonot asurot zo im zo and one and three are אסורות
asurot one against the other. Okay so that we saw in the
משנה Mishnah but that was only said in the name of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. ואמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב V’amar Rav
Chama bar Guriya amar Rav הלכה כרבי שמעון. Halakha k’Rabbi Shimon. We
rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Oh it's all very nice where's
the opposing position? So the גמרא says ומאן פליג עליה u’man palig
alei who is the opposing position? רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now this
is very strange we didn't see an opposing position in our משנה
Mishnah we you know how do you even know it's רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? So רש"י Rashi tells us try to figure out how
the גמרא knows it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But for our purposes
we'll accept that the גמרא understands that this is a רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon position and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees and we rule
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Now we just got through saying רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon versus רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we rule like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So you see that these rules aren't true. So
the גמרא says והא אמרת רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון הלכה כרבי יהודה
V’ha amart Rabbi Yehuda v’Rabbi Shimon Halakha k’Rabbi Yehuda didn't you tell
me we're all supposed to go like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? אלא
שמע מינה Ella shma mina so come you can see from this
says רב משארשיא Rav Mesharshiya ליתנהו leisnehu these rules aren't true we
don't go by them. And here the גמרא makes a very important
qualification about what does it mean to go by these rules and
we'll end with this for today. So the גמרא says ומה קשיא
u’mai kushya why is that a challenge? דילמא היכא דאיתמר איתמר היכא
דלא איתמר לא איתמר Dilma heicha d’itmar itmar heicha d’lo itmar lo
itmar meaning no when we say these rules it doesn't mean we
never פוסקין poskin the other position. It means if there's if it
was said we פוסקין poskin A over B in a particular case
fine. It's always possible in any particular case we'll rule with one
opinion as opposed to the other. The principle about these כללי klalei
the point of these כללים klalim is היכא דלא איתמר heicha d’lo
itmar where we don't know how to פסקן. pasken. We don't have
a tradition who was right it's not clear who was right. When
you don't know how to פסקן pasken you go by these rules.
But if it actually was said which position we go by it's
not these rules are 100% of the time they're rules you use
when you don't know how to פסקן pasken and when there isn't
evidence about how you פסקן. pasken. Okay so we'll see more about
that tomorrow.